A Guide to the Laurance S. Rockefeller photographs, Photo Files, RG 1 FA1128
Rockefeller Archive Center
Laurance S. Rockefeller photographs, Photo Files, RG 1
1880s-2004
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, Laurance Spelman
Rockefeller, Mary French
FA1128
83 Cubic Feet
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (CDs) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Biographical / Historical
Laurance Spelman Rockefeller was born on May 26, 1910, in New York City, the fourth of the six children of John D. Rockefeller, Jr. and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller. He attended Lincoln School, a progressive coeducational preparatory school connected with Teachers College of Columbia University in New York City, before entering Princeton in 1928. A philosophy major, he graduated from Princeton in 1932 with a B.A. degree in philosophy and went on to two years of graduate study at Harvard Law School.
On August 15, 1934, Laurance Rockefeller married Mary French in the Congregational Church in Woodstock, Vermont. Together they raised three daughters and a son.
During World War II, Laurance Rockefeller served in the Navy (1942-1945), attaining the rank of lieutenant commander.
Laurance Rockefeller pursued a number of successful careers during his lifetime. He was a pioneer in the field of venture capital. He was a leading and influential figure for three decades in the American conservation movement. He led the development of one of the world's foremost cancer care and research facilities, and was both a benefactor and advisor to major educational institutions. And, with great foresight, he combined his personal vision for conservation, recreation, and the spiritual needs of individuals to develop internationally acclaimed environmentally oriented resorts. His many accomplishments have been recognized both nationally and internationally.
In 1935, he began working in the family office in Rockefeller Center. His first duties were to develop his knowledge and understanding of Rockefeller philanthropic activities, conservation projects, and business interests, through both study and playing a modest role in their operation. Simultaneously, he developed his own special interest, blending business acumen with the talents of a "gadgeteer," a label he once pinned on himself.
He became well known as an investor of risk capital in young enterprises whose future was based primarily on scientific and technological developments. Over the years his investment interests included the fields of aviation, aerospace, electronics, high temperature physics, composite materials, optics, lasers, data processing, thermionics, instrumentation, and nuclear power. Beginning in August 1969, his venture capital investments in these areas were made through a venture capital group, Venrock, formed by members of the Rockefeller family.
In a different area of venture capital, he developed outstanding environmentally oriented resort hotels in Puerto Rico, the Virgin Islands, Hawaii, and Vermont, serving as chairman of Rockresorts, Inc., a resort management company which he founded and chaired.
Conservation of the environment and recreational development constituted much of Laurance Rockefeller's philanthropy and public service. His introduction to public service came in 1939 when Governor Herbert H. Lehman of New York appointed him to the Palisades Interstate Park Commission (PIPC). He was president of the PIPC from 1970 to 1977 and continued as a commissioner until his resignation in December 1978. He was an advisor to Presidents Eisenhower, Kennedy, Johnson, Nixon, and Ford on matters of environmental conservation and outdoor recreation, and he worked on federal commissions set up to help develop national conservation and environmental policies and programs. In 1958, President Dwight D. Eisenhower appointed him chairman of the Outdoor Recreation Resources Review Commission (ORRRC), which charted ways of meeting the nation's outdoor recreation needs through the year 2000. He was a special emissary for President Lyndon Johnson in the effort that led to creation of the National Redwoods Park in California, and he served as chairman of President Nixon's Citizens' Advisory Committee on Environmental Quality, successor to a similar group which he headed under President Johnson. He played a pivotal role in the creation and development of several national parks including Grand Teton National Park in Wyoming, Virgin Islands National Park on the island of St. John, and Marsh-Billings-Rockefeller National Historical Park in Vermont.
He served as a leader of several important nonprofit and philanthropic organizations. He was president and later chairman of the Rockefeller Brothers Fund (1958-1980) and was a trustee of the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation (1960-1982). His first association with Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center in New York City was in 1947; he also served as chairman (1960-1982), overseeing an expansion and modernization of its operations. He was a longtime trustee of the New York Zoological Society (1935-1986) and served as its president (1969-1971) and chairman (1971-1985).
Laurance Rockefeller received many honors for his efforts on behalf of the environment and cancer research and treatment. Among them are the Alfred P. Sloan, Jr. Memorial Award from the American Cancer Society (1969), the Medal of Freedom (1969), Commander (Honorary) of the Most Excellent Order of the British Empire (1971), the Woodrow Wilson Award from Princeton University (1991), the Congressional Gold Medal (1991), the Chairman's Award from the National Geographic Society (1995), the Theodore Roosevelt National Park Medal of Honor (1995), and the Lady Bird Johnson Conservation Award for Lifetime Achievement (1997). In 2003, he became the first person to be made an honorary citizen of the British Virgin Islands in recognition of his many contributions to the area. In December 1959 he received the National Institute of Social Sciences' Gold Medal for distinguished services to humanity, an award previously bestowed upon his grandfather and father. This was the first time in the Institute's history that three generations of a family had been so honored. The citation to Laurance Rockefeller proclaimed him as a "creative organizer of ventures into new fields of human endeavor for the growing aspirations of mankind; [and a] leader in the conservation of natural resources and in the development of the medical and social sciences for the welfare of the individual." In 1967, the National Institute awarded Gold Medals to all five Rockefeller brothers in recognition of their individual and collective services to humanity.
Laurance Rockefeller died on July 11, 2004, at his home in Manhattan.
Prepared by Rockefeller Family and Associates, June 1982, and 2004.
Scope and Contents
FA1128 (LSR Photographs, RG 1, Photo Files) contains the bulk of LSR's loose photographic prints from his home and his office, along with some albums and slides. RG 1 is a composite collection. It contains LSR's loose or "flat" photo files, but also materials that for various reasons were not included in the other collection components at the time the collection was organized. RG 1 encompasses personal and family photos, as well as photographic documentation of LSR's business and civic activities. The Rockefeller Family Office's Public Relations files on Laurance and Mary French Rockefeller have also been included as a series in RG 1. Similarly, the photographs and albums from the former Series 1009 Photos (LSR Family) are now interfiled with RG 1.
Within FA1128, materials are arranged into series according to subject and then by particular subject or subheading within these categories. The finding aid descriptions for FA1128 follow this subject arrangement without regard to format, but oversized materials are housed in a separately numbered series of boxes (labeled O 1 – O 145).
Photos sized between 5"x7" and 8"x10" were considered part of the "5000" series of photos, and they received a 4-digit identifying number (starting with 5000). We have included these 5000-series photo identification numbers in notes at the file level, but there is no general index to these numbers. In addition, other photos carry a "photo index number" (also noted in file-level notes), which refers to a reference file created as part of a LSR-biography project. The photo index files are found in FA1128D, RG 5, LSR Photo Reference Files.
Arrangement
The LSR Photograph collection is sorted into several component groupings, loosely based on format, or storage location (home or office), or use (e.g., Photo Reference files), at the time his collection was arranged and catalogued. RG 1 (FA1128) contains LSR's loose or "flat" photo files, plus materials that were not included in other collection components at the time the collection was organized. RG 2 (FA1128A) contains LSR's Albums (up to the late-1980s); RG 3 (FA1128B) consists of LSR's Slide Books; RG 4 (FA1128C) contains LSR's Snapshot Files; and RG 5 (FA1128D) comprises LSR's Photo Reference Files.
In organizing his collection, LSR's photo curators employed a system of numerical categories to arrange the material according to subject:
000 Art,
100 Family,
200 Houses,
300 Miscellaneous,
400 Civic,
500 Travel,
600 Resorts,
700 Spirituality.
These classifications generally carried throughout the collection, with some variations or elaboration. (Series 400 - Civic, for example, may include a broad range of subheadings covering Business, Education, Health and Hospitals, Federal Government, etc.)
Within FA1128, materials are arranged into series according to subject and then by particular subject or subheading within these categories. The subjects generally correspond to LSR's numerical schema (though some subcategories have been elevated to series), but for the most part the photos in RG 1 do not carry these numerical labels. Series are arranged in alphabetical order by subject name.
RG 1 is arranged into thirteen series: 1 – Art; 2 – Awards; 3 – Business; 4 – Civic; 5 – Houses; 6 – Individuals and Dignitaries; 7 – Religion and Spirituality; 8 – Resorts; 9 – Laurance S. Rockefeller and Family; 10 – Travel; 11 – Vessels; 12 – Woodstock; 13 – Public Relations.
Photographs
- Art, 1929 - 1999, undated; 1
  - General, 1929 - 1999, undated; 1
    - Art: General, Undated; Color prints, 3.5 x 5 - 8x10; 1 color negative. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Rod Goebel oil painting "Lewis River Falls"; Yin and Yang gilded sculpture; Renaissance painting; sculpted bust (unidentified); unidentified stone sculpture of nesting bird; color negative of J. G. Tyler painting of "America and the Coquette at Storm King on the Hudson." Includes photos nos. 5000-5002.
    - Art: Out, 1998; 2 Color polaroids and copies. Removed from album. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Photos of childhood painting by Larry Rockefeller (with letter returning it to him); painted portrait of Marion R. Weber (LSR took to JY Ranch). Photos separated from Album containing photos of paintings given to MSKCC in 1998.
    - American Indian Art, 1929-1930, undated; Black and white (sepia) prints, 3x5-6x9; 1 color 5x7 print. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Photos of paintings by various artists; photos nos. 5003 a-l. Penciled markings on back indicate pieces that were framed and/or exhibited.
    - China, Undated; Color transparencies, 5x7. Removed from paper frame mounts. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Green Fitzhugh china. Some pieces were included in the Sotheby's sale, 2005 October 11-12, lots 212-214.
    - Gifts to Society of Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center, 1999; OVERSIZED - Polaroid photos mounted in 10.5 x 12.5 album with magnetic pages. (Box O 1)
      Photos of items from the art collection of Laurance S. Rockefeller given to the Society of MSKCC. Includes title and artist information and valuation (or sale price?).
    - Gifts to Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center Art Committee (Art - Out), 1998; 12 Color polaroid prints in photo pages, 6.75 x 12.5. Removed from album. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Captioned polaroid photos of paintings given to MSKCC Art Committee, mainly 1998 July 21. Pages removed from ring-bound album.
    - Hudson River School Painting, Undated; OVERSIZED Black and white 7.5 x 15.5 print. (Box O 39)
      Early photograph of unidentified Hudson River School painting.
    - Maze, Paul, 1953, undated; Black and white prints, 4x8-6x8. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Paintings of coronation procession and guards, New York bridges and skyline. Photos nos. 5004-5011.
    - McClintock, Walter, Photographs, Undated; OVERSIZED colored 8x10 printed images on 11x14 mats (9 pieces) (Box O 2)
      Series of prints of Walter McClintock photos of western scenes and Blackfoot Indians. Nine prints: Bear Grass in Bloom; Foothills of Rocky Mountains, Meadow of Blue Lupine at sunset; Blackfoot Camp on Prairie (Eagle Tepee, Thunder, Serpent, Buffalo); Tribal Camp from Distance; Indian Scout; Grass Dancers Seated; Night Gun (a costume of a Grass Dancer); Night Singer; Blackfoot Camp (moonlight). Prints signed (on mat) "W. McC." Prints originally housed in sleeves numbered 1-10 (number 8 not in file).
    - Paintings and Artwork, Undated; 8x10 black and white prints (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Charles Uht photos of various paintings, watercolors, sculptures, etc. in LSR's collection. Duplicate copies of many images in LSR Art Binders.
    - Paintings: Echo Acre, 1994; Color 4x6 prints in photo pages. 56 images. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Paintings by various artists, at LSR's Echo Acres house in Vermont.
    - Paintings: Miss Julia Mott, 1981; Black and white 8x10 prints and negatives. (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Prints and negatives relating to restoration work on portrait of Miss Julia Mott by Gainsborough. Includes labels removed from frame at the time.
    - Porcelain, Undated; Two albums (6.25 x 10.75) with flip-file pages. (Box O 3)
      Card file and photographs of porcelain china collection. Cards detail pattern, holdings, provenance, and appraisal values.
    - Porcelain, Undated; Color prints, cut and glued to mat board. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Meissen Birds and Sevres "Beau Bleu" Service (armorial and ornithological, known as the Sudell Service). Photos showing arrangement of porcelain in display units at 834 Fifth Avenue, including accordian-folded card with photos of each shelf and unit.
    - Porcelain and Paintings, Undated; Color prints, in page sleeves. Removed from album. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Sets of china, vases, figurines, and some paintings, on display at 834 Fifth Avenue. Pages removed from ring-bound album.
    - Remington, Frederick, Undated; Color 5x7 print; 2 color slides. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Bronze sculpture, "Coming through the Rye." Note in file: "Remington statue in library - the original at Princeton." Photo no. 5012; slides (showing statue at JY Ranch) marked 200,112. Slides and print dated August 1978.
    - Rockefeller Center Office, 1991; Color 4x6 prints. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Artwork in LSR office; busts of JDR Sr. and Jr. Prints dated July 1991.
    - Rockefeller Center Office, Undated; Color polaroid prints, mounted on sheets of paper. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Buddhas and decorative objects in LSR's Office and LSR Conference Room (formerly NAR's office), Room 5600. Photos numbered, presumably corresponding to appraisal or inventory descriptions.
    - Rockefeller Center Office, Undated; Color photocopies. (Box 1, Folder 14 A)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Restricted - confidential material.
      Buddhas and decorative objects in LSR's Office and LSR Conference Room, Room 5600. Photocopy of the file. Photocopied sheets include some notations on Family selections.
    - Sculpture, Undated; OVERSIZED three 8x10 prints in 11x14 mats. (Box O 1)
      Sculpture of bather putting up her hair (Maillol?). 3 views. Box marked "Sculpture in Garden." Prints matted; stamped on back Alec Marshall.
    - Silver, Undated; Black and white 8x10 prints (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Charles Uht photos of silver in LSR's collection.
    - Silver, Undated; Black and white 8x10 prints; 2 color prints (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Charles Uht photos of silver in LSR's collection. Also includes two images of silver display cabinets at 834 Fifth Avenue.
    - Silver, Undated; Color 4x6 prints in album pages (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Various silver pieces at 834 Fifth Avenue. Images carry a number or an alpha-numerical designation.
  - Art (Binders), 2
    - Arrangements (Sevres Porcelain, NY), Undated; Black and white 8x10 prints in loose file (binder discarded). (Box O 4)
      Arrangements binder consists of 10 pages of photos of display shelves with Sevres porcelain dinner service, at 834 Fifth Avenue. Binder also refers to arrangements at Tarrytown (Pocantico), but they are not found in the file. Pages have been removed from the binder.
    - China 1, Undated; Black and white 8x10 prints in postbound binder. (Box O 5)
      Covered urns and vases; Lamp Bases; Services.
    - China 2, Undated; Black and white 8x10 prints in postbound binder. (Box O 6)
      Candelabra; Figurines; Miscellaneous; Glass
    - Furniture 1, Undated; Black and white 8x10 prints in postbound binder. (Box O 7)
    - Furniture 2 - 3, Undated; Black and white 8x10 prints in postbound binder (Furniture 2) or loose file. (Box O 8)
      Furniture 3 consists of only 4 pages, which have been removed from the binder.
    - Furniture - Woodstock, Undated; Black and white 8x10 prints in postbound binder. (Box O 9)
      Photos of furniture and rooms, without captions or labels. File includes some loose photos by Charles Uht.
    - Miscellaneous, Undated; Black and white 8x10 prints in loose file (binder discarded). (Box O 4)
      Miscellaneous binder consists of 17 pages concerning ceramics and pottery, screens, textiles, silhouettes, collages, and mosaics. Pages have been removed from the binder.
    - Paintings 1 (1 - 70), Undated; Black and white 8x10 prints in postbound binder. (Box O 10)
      Painting numbers Ptg 1-Ptg 70.
    - Paintings 2 (71 - 134), Undated; Black and white 8x10 prints in postbound binder. (Box O 11)
      Painting numbers Ptg 71- Ptg 134.
    - Paintings 3 (135 - 232), Undated; Black and white 8x10 prints in postbound binder. (Box O 12)
      Painting numbers Ptg 135- Ptg (232). There are several gaps in the numbers.
    - Pastels (1 - 48), Undated; Black and white 8x10 prints in postbound binder. (Box O 13)
      Pastels and Drawings numbers PST 1 - PST 48. Includes portraits of LSR children by Candler (1938-1947) and of LSR by Emmet (circa 1911).
    - Prints (1 - 105), Undated; Black and white 8x10 prints in postbound binder. (Box O 14)
      Print numbers 1-105, with several gaps.
    - Sculpture 1, Undated; Black and white 8x10 prints in postbound binder. (Box O 15)
      Arranged alphabetically by artist, followed by geographical arrangement
    - Sculpture 2, Undated; Black and white 8x10 prints in postbound binder. (Box O 16)
      Asian sculpture.
    - Silver 1, Undated; Black and white 8x10 prints in postbound binder. (Box O 17)
      Tea and Coffee Pots; Trophies. Includes LSR's trophies for Gymkhanas 1920-1921, at Bar Harbor and Pine Lodge. Also JDR Jr. trophy cup for Alaska trip, 1899.
    - Silver 2, Undated; Black and white 8x10 prints in postbound binder. (Box O 18)
      Cups, Porringers, and Mugs; Pitchers; Candlesticks; Salts, Peppers, and Mustards. Includes note: "All items do not appear in their correct categories in these albums, as pieces from more than one category were sometimes photographed together."
    - Silver 3, Undated; Black and white 8x10 prints in postbound binder. (Box O 19)
      Trays, Plates, and Platters; Dishes and Bowls
    - Silver 4, Undated; Black and white 8x10 prints in postbound binder. (Box O 20)
      Flatware; Miscellaneous Dining Room Pieces. Includes note: "All items do not appear in their correct categories in these albums, as pieces from more than one category were sometimes photographed together."
    - Silver 5, Undated; Black and white 8x10 prints in postbound binder. (Box O 21)
      Children's pieces; Miscellaneous Non-Dining Room (e.g., frames). Includes note: "All items do not appear in their correct categories in these albums, as pieces from more than one category were sometimes photographed together."
    - Watercolors 1 (1 - 69), Undated; Black and white 8x10 prints in postbound binder. (Box O 22)
      Watercolor numbers WC 1 - WC 69.
    - Watercolors 2 (70 - 149) - 3 (150 - 160), Undated; Black and white 8x10 prints in postbound binder (Watercolors 2) or loose file. (Box O 23)
      Binder 2 contains numbers WC 70 - WC 149. Watercolors 3 contains only 10 pages (WC 150 - 160; no WC 159), which have been removed from the binder.
- Awards, 1940 - 2003; 2
  - Awards: General (Albums), 1940-1975; Two OVERSIZED 15.5 x 17.5 albums containing certificates, documents, and 11 x 14 black and white and color photos. (Box O 24)
    Two binder albums containing various awards and certificates LSR received between 1940-1967 and 1968-1975, plus photographs of plaques and awards. A few photos at the back of the second album show the awards hanging on the walls of LSR's 834 Fifth Avenue apartment.
  - Awards: General (Albums), 1974-1977; OVERSIZED black and white 11x14 prints. (Box O 24)
    Awards from Arbor Day, Grand Teton National Park, and the Wings Club. Three images only, removed from a third, incomplete album.
  - Awards: General, 1973, undated; Black and white circa 8x10 prints and color 8.5 x 11.5 prints. (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Photos of LSR, receiving medal from Prince Bernhard, 1973; photos of two medallions: Commander of the Order of the Lion (Belgium), and Ordre des Arts et Lettres (France).
  - American Cancer Society, Alfred P. Sloan Jr. Memorial Award, 1969; 2 Black and white 8x10 glossy prints. (Box 2, Folder 19)
    LSR receiving first Alfred P. Sloan Jr. award, with copy of remarks by Thomas J. Watson Jr. Includes photo no. 5342.
  - British Virgin Islands, 1971; Black and white 5x7 prints. One print damaged from oil or liquid. (Box 2, Folder 20)
    LSR awarded medal of the Order of the British Empire, October 25, 1971. With Allston Boyer. (Photo nos. 5175-5176.)
  - British Virgin Islands' Belonger Ceremony, 2003 September 26; OVERSIZED Album (9x 10.5 x 1.75) with color 4x6 prints. (Box O 25)
    Album of photos from ceremony awarding LSR honorary citizenship in the British Virgin Islands, in recognition of contributions to conservation and economic development in the BVI. Ceremony held at 834 Fifth Avenue apartment. Includes LSR, Winthrop P. Rockefeller, Peter Jennings, and Hon. D. Orlando Smith. Album presented to LSR around May 2004.
  - British Virgin Islands' Belonger Ceremony, 2003 September 26; One 8x10 color print. (Box 2, Folder 21)
    Group photo of LSR, Winthrop P. Rockefeller, Peter Jennings, and Hon. D. Orlando Smith, at ceremony at 834 Fifth Avenue. Photo removed from frame.
  - Congressional Gold Medal, 1991 September 27; Oversized Leather album 11.25 x 10.5, magnetic pages with mainly color 7 x 10 prints. (Box O 25)
    Presentation of the Congressional Gold Medal to Laurance S. Rockefeller by President George H. W. Bush, The White House, September 27, 1991. Album with photos from the event, along with the text of the Senate and House bills, the Act (May 17, 1990), the White House Press Release, and LSR's remarks.
  - Congressional Gold Medal, 1991 September 27; Color and one black and white, 8x10 prints (Box 2, Folder 22)